So over the last lectures I showed you a lot how you can get data.
Bu yzden son konferanslarda size veri nasl elde edebileceinizi gstereceim.
Now of course I also want to show you how you can post data to a server and for that we get the add a
imdi tabii ki bir sunucudaki verileri nasl gnderebileceinizi ve Debbie'nin reklam bir
post area here at the bottom,
alt yaz alanna gtrdn gstermek istiyorum.
it's managed by the new post component which is a class based component which manages its own state
Kendi durumunu yneten ve dolaysyla bir kapsayc olan snf temelli bir bileen olan yeni
and hence is in a container because we're not passing or distributing the state to any other components.
posta bileeni tarafndan ynetiliyor nk devleti baka bir bileene datmyor ya da datmyoruz.
And now I want to hook up this add post button to essentially send a POST request to our dummy backend.
Ve imdi bu reklam mesaj dmesini, bunun iin Dammy arka umza esas olarak bir POST istei gndermek
For this, I'll
iin balamak istiyorum.
first of all add a method, the postDataHandler or post post handler if you want to do it
Her eyden nce, posta veri ileyicisine bir Mesaj cetini ekleyin veya isterseniz posta ileyicisini ekleyin.
and then there of course I need to use axios
Ve tabii ki x evet kullanmam gerekiyor.
Now first of all let's hook this method up by adding the on click listener down there, this
imdi her eyden nce bu mesajn zerine bir ileyici ekleyin tklama dinleyicisi ekleyerek bu yntemi
postDataHandler
umut edelim.
and now let's import axios so we that we can send a post request.
imdi de yl gndermelim, bylece bir posta talebi gnderebiliriz.
Now sending post requests
imdi istek gnderme dnn.
still use the axios object
Hala axes nesnesini kullann.
but now of course not the get method but the post method.
Ancak elbette get yntemi deil, post yntemi.
The post mehtod still takes a URL as an input and for our dummy backend, we can simply use the same
bunu basite kullanabiliriz, aksi takdirde alma istei iin kullandk, ayrca post isteklerini kabul eder.
URL we used for the get request, it also accepts post requests.
Yaz yine de bir girdi olarak alrsa ve kukla arka u iin
Now a post request needs more than the URL though, it needs a second argument which is the data we want
Artk bir post istei, Eldo'dan ok daha fazlasna ihtiya duyuyor, nk gndermek istediimiz verinin ikinci
to send because obviously a post request without data doesn't make that much sense.
bir argmanna ihtiya duyuyoruz. Akas, veriler olmadan yazlan bir talep bu kadar mantkl.
The data I want to send is a javascript object which contains title, body and author of a post.
Gndermek istediim veri balk gvdesi ve bir yayn teklifi ieren bir javascript nesnesidir.
So I'll create a new constant which should be a javascript object and there i'll set a title to this.
Bu yzden, bir javascript nesnesi olmas gereken yeni bir sabit oluturacam ve bu devlet
state.title,
balna bir balk ayarlayacam.
I'll set the body to this.state.content and you can of course choose any properties you want here for that
Cesedi bu devlet ieriine ayarlayacam ve o nesne iin istediiniz
object and I will set the author to this state of author.
zellikleri seebileceksiniz ve teklifi bu teklifte sunacam.
Again you can add more,
Yine daha fazlasn ekleyebilirsiniz.
you can expand this form here at the bottom of course.
Bu formu tablonun alt ksmnda geniletebilirsiniz.
Then I will said post, this constant here as a second argument to the post method
Sonra bu sabit ikinci argman post yntemi yazlan syledi.
and of course, this is just called post because what we are submitting is some data about a post, you can name
Ve elbette bu sadece posta olarak adlandrlabilir, nk yeniden yaynlamann ismini yazabileceiniz bir yaynla ilgili baz veriler
this whatever you want,
istediiniz zamanki gibi yapar.
you can also name this data.
Ayrca veri olarak isim verebilirsiniz.
Now you can also pass a third argument to configure this request but we don't need that
Artk bu istei yaplandrmak iin nc bir argman da iletebilirsiniz, ancak buna gerek yoktur.
here. Important for us,
Bizim iin nemlisin.
This of course is a javascript object but axios will automatically basically stringify this, so
Bu elbette bir javascript nesnesidir, ancak Access otomatik olarak temel olarak savalar dizileyecek ve bylece bizi
turn this into json data,
Jason veri haline getirecektir.
it will do it for us just as it extract the json data and get requests for us too.
Komu verileri kard gibi bizim iin de yapacak ve bizim iin de talepler alacak.
And now this also of course runs asynchronously,
Ve imdi tabii ki zaman uyumsuz olarak alyor.
we can listen to the response just like we can do it for get requests and we can print it to the console
stei almak iin yapabileceimiz gibi tepkiyi de dinleyebilir ve buradan
here.
konsola sunabiliriz.
Now let's try this out,
imdi bunu deneyelim.
let's save this,
unu kurtaralm.
let's open the console and let's enter some content here,
Konsolu aalm ve burada biraz ierik girelim.
this is some test content, maybe switch the author to Manu and hit add post.
Baz test ierii, size teklifte bulunmak ve reklam yaynlamak isterseniz gei yapabilir mi?
And here's the response, status text 201 which indicates that it was successful. And now that the dummy backend
Ve ite baarl olduunu belirten yant durumu metni 201 ve imdi buraya geri
here won't store the data of course, it just returns the data in the response so that we can see
dnen kukla elbette verileri saklamayacak, yanta veri dndryor, bylece baaryla
that we did send it successfully and looks like we did,
gnderdiimizi ve grebildiimizi grebiliyoruz yaptk.
this is the data
Bunu bugne kadar yapyor mu?
we did send. Again for a real server of course, for your own server
Elbette kendi sunucunuz iin gerek bir sunucu iin tekrar gnderdik.
you probably have some logic on the server to then also store this in the database.
Muhtemelen veritabannda saklanan dentaller iin sunucuda baz mantk var.
This is how we can post data, that is all there's to it. Just exchanging the word here, the name of the
te biz sadece bu kelimeyi yntemin adyla deitirip veriyi ikinci bir argman olarak
method and passing the data as a second argument
geirerek yapmak iin gereken tm bilgileri veriyoruz.
and now we can also send data to servers.
Ve imdi de sunuculara veri gnderebiliriz.